A Guide to John Henry Ingram's Poe Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Part One: Letters, Manuscripts, Other Documents
  - MARIA CLEMM, Fordham, letter to MARIE LOUISE SHEW HOUGHTON, 1847 February [Friday].; [34]; Copy by Mrs. Houghton. 4 pp. (Box 1)
    Mrs. Clemm expresses her appreciation for medicines and wines Mrs. Houghton had sent shortly before Virginia's death and during Edgar's sickness.
  - POE, New York, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1847 March 11.; [35]; Copy by Eveleth. 2 pp. (Box 1)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Text printed in Letters 2: 348-349.
  - POE, New York, letter to MESSRS. J. F. REINMAN and J. H. WALKER, 1847 March 11.; [36]; Copy by William Hand Browne. 1 p. (Box 1)
    Text printed in Letters 2: 349-350.
  - POE, [Fordham], letter to MARIE LOUISE SHEW HOUGHTON, 1847 [May].; [37]; Copy by E. Dora Houghton. 2 pp. (Box 1)
    Text printed in Letters 2: 350-351.
  - POE'S "THE BELLS", 1847.; [38]; Facsimile of four stanzas in Poe's MS. 4 pp. (Box 1)
  - "LIKE ALL TRUE SOULS OF NOBLE BIRTH," verses by MARY GOVE NICHOLS, 1847?.; [39]; MS. copy by E. Dora Houghton. 1 p. (Box 1)
    Mrs. Nichols sent this as a valentine to Marie Louise Shew (Mrs. Houghton), and Poe copied it in her autograph book. See Item 213.
  - POE, New York, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1848 January 4.; [40]; Copy by Eveleth. 4 pp. (Box 1)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Text printed in Letters 2: 354-357.
  - POE, New York, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1848 February 29.; [41]; Copy by Eveleth. 10 pp. (Box 1)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Text printed in Letters 2: 360-362.
  - POE'S "TO MARIE LOUISE", 1848 February.; [42]; Tracing of Poe's 32-line MS. 2 pp. (Box 1)
    Enclosed in Item 210. Marie Louise Shew Houghton sent the original MS. to Ingram in 1875.
  - POE, Fordham, letter to ANNA BLACKWELL, Providence, 1848 June 14.; [43]; Copy by Sarah Helen Whitman. 3 pp. (Box 1)
    Enclosed in Item 211. Text printed in Letters 2: 369-371.
  - "ERMINA'S TALE," a poem of 30 4-line stanzas by Jane E. Locke, 1848 August.; [44]; MS. in Mrs. Locke's hand. 4 pp. (Box 1)
    Copy reached Ingram through Annie Richmond. [See Item 318.] In a note appended, presumably to Poe, Mrs. Locke asks that receipt of this MS. be acknowledged immediately.
  - POE, Fordham, letter to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, 1848 October 1.; [45]; Copy by Mrs. Whitman. 15 pp. (Box 1)
    Text printed in Letters 2: 382-391. In a note appended to this copy, Mrs. Whitman asks Ingram to hold this letter sacred for Poe and for herself. She knows he will not say of it, as did Richard Henry Stoddard, "Curious, very curious, indeed."
  - POE, Fordham, letter to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, 1848 [October 18.].; [46]; Extracts copied by Mrs. Whitman. 7 pp. (Box 1)
    Text printed in Letters 2: 391-398.
  - POE, aboard New York steamboat, letter to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, 1848 November 14.; [47]; Copy by Mrs. Whitman. 1 p. (Box 1)
    Text printed in Letters 2: 400.
  - POE, Fordham, letter to ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, 1848 November 16.; [48]; Copy by Mrs. Richmond. 4 pp. (Box 1)
    Text printed in Letters 2: 400-404. "This must be burnt," written by Ingram on this copy.
  - POE, New York, letter to EDWARD V. VALENTINE, 1848 November 20.; [49]; Copy by Valentine. 1 p. (Box 1)
    Text printed in Letters 2: 404, where variants are noted.
  - POE, Fordham, letter to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, 1848 [November] 24.; [50]; Facsimile of 8-line fragment. 1 p. (Box 1)
    Text printed in Letters 2: 406-409. Mrs. Whitman sent this fragment for Ingram's use in his 1874-75 edition of Poe's works. Facsimile faces p. lxvi of vol. I.
  - POE, Fordham, letter to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, 1848 November 26.; [51]; Copy by Mrs. Whitman. 2 pp. (Box 1)
    Text printed in Letters 2: 409-411.
  - MARIA CLEMM, Fordham, letter to ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, 1848 November? December?.; [52]; ALS. 16-line fragment. 1 p. (Box 1)
    Mrs. Clemm doubts the wisdom of Poe's marrying Sarah Helen Whitman and thanks Annie for inducing him to make to her the promise which Mrs. Clemm is sure he will die before he breaks. Mrs. Richmond's note on margin: "It is the letter containing this promise she [Mrs. Clemm] borrowed and never returned!"
  - POE, Fordham, to WILLIAM J. PABODIE, Providence, 1848 December 4.; [53]; ALS. Facsimile. 1 p. (Box 1)
    Text printed in Letters 2: 411-412. At Sarah Helen Whitman's request, Poe wrote this letter to Pabodie signing it with his full name, since Pabodie wanted an autograph he could "show." Pabodie willed it to Mrs. Whitman in 1870; sometime later she gave it to Thomas C. Latto who lent it back to her for Ingram's use in 1874. Ingram had this facsimile made and reproduced it in his "Memoir" in his edition of Poe's works, Vol. 1, between pp. lxxvi and lxxvii.
  - POE, New York, letter to SARAH ANNA LEWIS, 1848?.; [54]; Written on Mrs. Lewis' MS. of "The Prisoner of Perote," 4 pp. (Box 1)
    Text printed in Letters 2: 413-414.
  - POE, Fordham, letter to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, 1849 January 25.; [55]; Copy by Annie Richmond. 4 pp. (Box 1)
    Enclosed in Item 310. Text printed in Letters 2: 420-422. See Item 310.
  - POE, Fordham, letter to ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, 1849 February 19.; [56]; Copy by Mrs. Richmond. 5 pp. (Box 1)
    Text printed in Letters 2: 429-432. In an appended note, Mrs. Richmond explains to Ingram on 27 September 1876 Mr. Richmond's repudiation of the accusations made against Poe by the Locke family.
  - POE, New York, letter to JOHN R. THOMPSON, Richmond, 1849 May 10.; [57]; Copy by unidentified hand. 1 p. (Box 1)
    Text printed in Letters 2: 441.
  - POE, New York, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1849 June 26.; [58]; Copy by Eveleth. 2 pp. (Box 1)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Text printed in Letters 2: 449-450.
  - MARIA CLEMM, New York, letter to ANNIE RICHMOND, 1849 July 30.; [59]; Copy by Ingram. 1 p. (Box 1)
    Tells of Poe's derangement (in Philadelphia ) and of his fancied pursuit by the police. Poe assured her that he never did anything disgraceful while deranged.
  - MARIA CLEMM, New York, to ANNIE RICHMOND, Annisquam, MA, 1849 August 4.; [60]; ALS. 3 pp. (Box 1)
    Writes of her extreme anxiety over Poe's long absence and silence.
  - MARIA CLEMM, New York, to ANNIE RICHMOND, 1849 September 3.; [61]; ALS. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Still in despair over Poe's long silence, Mrs. Clemm wants to borrow money from Mr. Richmond so that she can go in search of Poe.
  - MARIA CLEMM, New York, to ANNIE RICHMOND, 1849 September 15.; [62]; ALS. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Mrs. Clemm has received Mr. Richmond's letter with $5 enclosed. Tells of having received a letter from Poe in Richmond and of the temperance pledge he enclosed, which she now sends to Mrs. Richmond.
  - POE, Richmond, letter to MARIA CLEMM, 1849 September 18.; [63]; Copy by Amelia Poe. 3 pp. (Box 2)
    Text printed in Letters 2: 461-462.
  - JOSEPH W. WALKER, Baltimore, letter to DR. JOSEPH E. SNODGRASS, Baltimore, 1849 October 3.; [64]; Copy by William Hand Browne. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 360. Text printed in A. H. Quinn's Edgar Allan Poe, p. 638.
  - POE'S OBITUARY. Written by SUSAN ARCHER TALLEY WEISS for the Richmond Republican, 1849 October 15.; [65]; MS. Copy by Edward V. Valentine. 9 pp. (Box 2)
  - MARIA CLEMM, Lowell, letter to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, 1849 October 26.; [66]; Copy by Ingram. 4 pp. (Box 2)
    Mrs. Clemm mentions Jane E. Locke, the Stanard family, General David Poe, Sr.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, letter to MARIA CLEMM, Lowell, 1849 October 28.; [67]; Copy by Amelia Poe. 2 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 428. Mrs. Whitman expresses her sympathy for Mrs. Clemm's sorrow over Poe's death.
  - MARIA CLEMM, Lowell, letter to NEILSON POE, Baltimore, 1849 November 1.; [68]; Copy by William Hand Browne. 2 pp. (Box 2)
    Mrs. Clemm asks that Poe's trunk be forwarded to her in Lowell and insists that her right to Poe's possessions as well as the profits from his books are greater than are Rosalie Poe's. Remarks that Longfellow has paid her a sympathetic visit.
  - POE'S "FOR ANNIE", 1849.; [69]; Facsimile of Poe's MS. 15 stanzas. 2 pp. (Box 2)
    Annie Richmond mailed this facsimile to Ingram on 14 January 1877. Poe had given the original to her, as the poem was printed in the Flag of Our Union and in the Home Journal.
  - POE'S "FOR ANNIE", 1849.; [70]; Facsimile of 15 lines from Poe's MS. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Poe incorporated these lines into his poem "A Dream Within a Dream" and gave the original MS. to Annie Richmond.
  - "THE LATE EDGAR ALLAN POE " -- letter from GEORGE R. GRAHAM to N. P. WILLIS, printed in "The Editor's Table," Graham's Magazine, 36 (March 1850): 224-226, 1850 February 2.; [71]; Copy by Sarah Helen Whitman. 12 pp. (Box 2)
  - MARIA CLEMM, Lowell, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1850 May 20.; [72]; Copy by Eveleth. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Eveleth's last letter to Poe was forwarded to Mrs. Clemm from Richmond after his death. Says she has not received one dollar from the sales of Poe's works; asks Eveleth to sell a few sets of Griswold's edition for her; begs him to disregard all the evil things said about Poe. If Eveleth writes to her, she will tell him all about Poe. Graham's for March has the truth about him.
  - MARIA CLEMM, Lowell, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1850 May 20.; [73]; Copy by Eveleth. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Mrs. Clemm is grateful and glad that Eveleth will try to sell some sets of Poe's works for her and that he does not believe all that he has heard against Poe. Will write that long letter promised.
  - MARIA CLEMM, Lowell, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1850 June 8.; [74]; Copy by Eveleth. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Unable at present to write that long letter about Poe.
  - MARIA CLEMM, Lowell, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1850 September 24.; [75]; Copy by Eveleth. 2 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Mrs. Clemm sends third volume of Poe's works. Says George R. Graham wrote her that he had a host of noble souls ready to refute the base exaggerations and vile misrepresentations Rufus Griswold has made against Poe. Admits there were times Poe was not conscious of what he wrote. Griswold has taken advantage of this.
  - MARIA CLEMM, Milford, CT, letter to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, 1852 November 7.; [76]; Copy by Ingram. 4 pp. (Box 2)
    Mentions Jane E. Locke, the Stanard family, General David Poe.
  - JOHN H. B. LATROBE, Baltimore, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1852 December 7.; [77]; Copy by Eveleth. 3 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Latrobe denies Griswold's statement that Poe won the Saturday Visiter prize only because his handwriting writing was legible. Describes the difficulty the Committee had in choosing a winning story from the rich contents of the "Tales of the Folio Club." When he met Poe after the prize was awarded, Latrobe was impressed by his eloquence and accuracy of minute detail in describing an imaginary voyage to the moon.
  - SARAH ELMIRA ROYSTER SHELTON, Richmond, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1852 December 22.; [78]; Copy by Eveleth. 2 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Mrs. Shelton still has a deep interest in Poe and the deepest respect for his memory. Believes him to have been misrepresented, but begs to be excused from communicating anything that would bring her before the public in any form whatever. Intends, when opportunity offers, to render some assistance to Mrs. Clemm.
  - ANNIE RICHMOND, Lowell, letter to MARIE LOUISE SHEW HOUGHTON, 1853 February 9.; [79]; Copy by Ingram. 2 pp. (Box 2)
    Mrs. Richmond laments the cruel suffering she has endured as a result of sharing her secrets and confidences with Mrs. Clemm.
  - JOHN P. KENNEDY, Baltimore, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1853 April 13.; [80]; Copy by Eveleth. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Kennedy agrees with Latrobe's statement about the manner in which the Baltimore Saturday Visiter prize was awarded to Poe. Lost sight of Poe after he left the Southern Literary Messenger. Kennedy heard stories that Poe was given to drink and dissipation; Thomas W. White told him that Poe could not be relied upon for work; and William E. Burton said the same.
  - J. S. REDFIELD, New York, ALS to MARIA CLEMM, 1853 April 26.; [81]; 2 pp. (Box 2)
    Redfield forwards to her a Bible and a prayer book which cost $7. Asks if Mrs. Clemm has received copyright pay for English, French, and German editions of Poe's works.
  - SARAH ANNA LEWIS, Brooklyn, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1854 January 3.; [82]; Copy by Eveleth. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Mrs. Lewis says Mrs. Clemm has been a member of her household for several months, that she knew much of Poe and that in her presence he was always the refined gentleman, scholar, and poet. Knows Griswold, too, and does not think he has consumption. Asks about John Neal's proposed critical survey of American literature. Denies that her name is Sarah Anna,although it was mistakenly printed so; it is Stella Anna, or Estelle Anna. Intends to place the remains of Poe and Virginia Poe in Greenwood Cemetery; this much done, their literary friends will probably erect a monument over their remains.
  - SARAH ANNA LEWIS, Brooklyn, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1854 February 11.; [83]; Copy by Eveleth. 2 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Mrs. Lewis does not believe that Poe was a drunkard or that he could have been a vulgar man, under any circumstances, but does not doubt that despair did sometimes drag him to the very verge of insanity. Poe dined with her at 3 p.m. and left at 5 p.m. for Richmond on 29 June 1849. She thinks she should see both Neal and Eveleth before they publish anything about Poe.
  - ANNE C. LYNCH, New York, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1854 March 8.; [84]; Copy by Eveleth. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Miss Lynch's relations with Poe were superficial rather than intimate; in consequence of a wide difference between them over his treatment of another lady, saw very little of him the last two or three years of his life. Never saw him under the influence of wine.
  - ANNE C. LYNCH, New York, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1854 March 19.; [85]; Copy by Eveleth. 2 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. In society Poe had the bearing and manner of a gentleman: his conversation was interesting; his manner polite and engaging; he was elegant in his toilet; he was quiet and unpretentious, never abstracted or dreamy; and he would never have attracted attention but for his strikingly intellectual head and features which bore the unmistakable character of genius. Not intimate with Poe and not under the influence he exercised over many.
  - SARAH ANNA LEWIS, Brooklyn, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1854 November 6.; [86]; Copy by Eveleth. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Mrs. Lewis saw Poe once or twice a month from January of 1847 until 29 June 1849. She freely admits having told Rufus Griswold that Poe had wanted him to become his editor, in case of his death, claiming that Poe had asked her to do it, for he had great confidence in Griswold's editorial ability. Poe and Griswold had become friends prior to Poe's departure for the South in June of 1849.
  - ELIZABETH F. ELLET, New York, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1856 April 5.; [87]; Copy by Eveleth. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Mrs. Ellet writes that she has always understood that Poe, though a man of genius, was intemperate and subject to attacks of lunacy and that he was frequently in the asylum.
  - JAMES W. DAVIDSON, Winnsboro, SC, AL to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, 1858 April 23.; [88]; Fragment. 4 pp. (Box 2)
    Davidson writes that he is deeply interested in efforts to vindicate Poe's character. His own defense of him was printed in Russell's Magazine (November 1857). Comments on John R. Thompson's conversation about Poe with Robert Browning and Elizabeth Barrett Browning. Offers a critical estimate of the truth in Harriet Beecher Stowe's book. Mrs. Whitman has written at the top of the letter a brief account of her own relationship to Davidson and of Davidson's relationship to Poe.
  - MARIA CLEMM, Alexandria, VA, to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, 1859 April 14 & 22.; [89]; Copies of extracts by Ingram. 2 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 138. Poe family history and biographical notes about Edgar Poe.
  - MARIA CLEMM, Alexandria, VA, letter to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, 1859 April 14.; [89-a]; Fragment in Ingram's hand. 2 pp. (Box 2)
    A variant of Item 89 with note appended by Mrs. Whitman on the persistence of Poe's love from Annie Richmond even were he to marry Mrs. Shelton.
  - JAMES W. DAVIDSON, Columbia, SC, AL to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, 1859 April 15.; [90]; Fragment. 2 pp. (Box 2)
    Thinks Anna Cora Mowatt Ritchie's letter about Poe seems to "get at" much that was poorly found by others before. Expresses enthusiasm over performance of singer Marietta Piccolomini.
  - WILLIAM WERTENBAKER'S STATEMENT ABOUT POE, 1860 May 12.; [92]; Copy by John Parker. 4 pp. (Box 2)
    In 1826 Dr. Socrates Maupin, Presiding Officer of the Faculty, directed William Wertenbaker to draw up this statement about Poe's scholarship and behavior at the University of Virginia in 1826. On 22 May 1860, Dr. Maupin appended a note to this statement attesting to its validity.
  - MARIA CLEMM, Alexandria, VA, letter to NEILSON POE, Baltimore, 1860 August 19.; [93]; Copy by Nathaniel Holmes Morison. 7 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 184. Biographical facts of Edgar's early life, description of his home life at Fordham, his work habits, his devotion to Virginia. Mrs. Clemm has heard that Edgar's grave is in the basement of the church in Baltimore, covered with rubbish and coal. Morison appends a note to Ingram denying the rumor about Poe's grave.
  - MARIA CLEMM, Alexandria, VA, letter to NEILSON POE, Baltimore, 1860 August 26.; [94]; Copy by Nathaniel Holmes Morison. 6 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 184. Edgar did not think it worth while during his lifetime to deny reports of his having travelled to Greece and Russia. After his death, Mrs. Clemm burned hundreds of letters written to him by literary ladies. Fearing poverty might induce her to accept Rufus Griswold's offer of $500 for the letters of a certain literary lady, she burned them, too. Other letters she gave to Griswold and now is unable to recover them from Griswold's executors. She has spent some time in Longfellow's house in Cambridge, MA, and he has recently asked for and received the last two of Poe's autographs that she had. Encloses two of Poe's letters to Neilson Poe, one written shortly before his death and the other written when Neilson offered to take Virginia into his home for several years.
  - MARIA CLEMM, Putnam, CT, AL to ANNIE RICHMOND, 1861 June 29.; [95]; Fragment. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Recalls that eleven years ago this day she looked upon her dear Eddie for the last time. Ingram corrects to read twelve years.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1864 December 15.; [96]; Copy by Eveleth. 3 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Mrs. Whitman has proof that Rufus Griswold purposely falsified Poe's MSS. and notes about him. Has seen a note Griswold wrote to a New York friend in 1850: "I am getting on rapidly with my Life of Poe and am trying hard to do him justice, for Fanny's spirit looks down on me while I write." Griswold could not forgive Poe the interest he had inspired in Mrs. Frances Sargent Osgood. Mrs. Whitman has proof, too, from the University of Virginia that Poe was not expelled. He did not graduate simply because at that time the University conferred no degree. Poe had told her of his intention to write a pendant to his "Domain of Arnheim," and after his death, when she first saw "Landor's Cottage," she realized that he had introduced into it the delicate tints of the wallpaper he had noticed and praised in the room in which they had been sitting as they talked.
  - "FAREWELL TO EARTH." Verses delivered by Miss Lizzie Doten, a trance speaker, in Clinton Hall, New York. Printed in Ryde Tracts, No. 3. 8 pp. "THE KINGDOM." A 6-stanza verse, taken from Poems from the Inner Life by Lizzie Doten, 1864.; [97]; MS. copy by Ingram. 2 pp. (Box 2)
    Both verses were allegedly delivered by Poe's departed spirit.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1865 January 15.; [98]; Copy by Eveleth. 2 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. There was a strange spiritual energy or effluence which seemed to surround Poe, acting on those en report with him. At one time she and Poe simultaneously received impressions of the original identity of the names Power ( Sarah Helen Whitman's maiden name) and Poe.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1865 February 27.; [99]; Copy by Eveleth. 3 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Poe saw her one July midnight in 1845; later he sent her anonymously the poem beginning "I saw thee once --once only...." A partially obscured date on the torn fly-leaf of an old family Bible fixes Mrs. Whitman's birth date, very likely, as 19 January 1803.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1866 January 17.; [100]; Copy by Eveleth. 2 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Since she cannot live much longer, Mrs. Whitman wishes to put into Eveleth's hand a statement about one of Rufus Griswold's myths, a statement only once before put into writing and to but one person, Sallie E. Robins. Had she not wished her book about Poe to be entirely impersonal, she could long ago have refuted Griswold's story of Poe's riotous conduct at the house of a New England lady having made necessary the summoning of police. She writes a summary of Poe's visit to Providence during which he had to be cared for by a doctor at the home of William J. Pabodie.
  - JAMES W. DAVIDSON, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1866 May 28.; [101]; Copy by Eveleth. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Davidson is grateful Eveleth has said in his memoranda in the Old Guard for June that much of Griswold's Memoir of Poe is untrue.
  - GEORGE W. EVELETH, Fairfield, IA, ALS to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, 1866 December 30.; [102]; 4 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 141. If Mrs. Whitman is to be the memorist of either of the two forthcoming editions of Poe's works, Eveleth will furnish for her use Poe's "Rejoinder" to Thomas Dunn English, a letter about the Poe-English quarrel, and a statement about the conclusion of "Marie Roget" that Poe made to him.
  - SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, Providence, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1867 March 2.; [103]; Copy by Eveleth. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Strangely, Mrs. Whitman has just seen a copy of the Round Table containing Eveleth's paragraph about Poe's "Marie Roget." Poe told her the fact Eveleth states [i.e., that the murderer had confessed] and said that the name of the young naval officer was Spencer.
  - WILLIAM D. O'CONNOR, Washington, DC, AL to SARAH HELEN WHITMAN, 1869 January.; [104]; Fragment. 8 pp. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 143. Walt Whitman is grateful for Mrs. Whitman's remarks relayed to him by O'Connor: "I kept back nothing of all you wrote, except one line, the one in which Jeannie Channing was reported as saying that W. W. loved me better than anyone living, which I guess is absurd and mistaken." Mentions Eugene Benson's article on Poe in the Galaxy, December 1868.
  - JAMES W. DAVIDSON, letter to GEORGE W. EVELETH, 1869 February 8.; [105]; Copy by Eveleth. 1 p. (Box 2)
    Enclosed in Item 340. Maria Clemm said years ago that Poe was in Europe only once, with the John Allan s. Poe's brother was the one in the St. Petersburg affair, an episode Edgar Poe attributed to himself, a course in keeping with his mental bent. He cared not a button for the Greeks, and still less, if possible, for liberty.